Samuel Oriaifo Oshio

Abuja, Federal Capital Territory, Nigeri



samueloshio5@gmail.com



+2348133082537



linkedin.com/in/samuel-oshio

Summary

Data Analyst with 3+ years of experience in the democratisation of data, information and insights as completely agile process projects maximising impact and delivering growth. Performed Analytics in a variety of data sources with accountabilities for all aspects of Data Strategy, Data Management, Information Management, Analytics, and Insights and simplified large volumes of information into thematic insights and conclusions. Successfully telling a story or narrative from the analysed data for executive view and generated key metrics, reports, and dashboards that provide visibility, insights, and accountability, identified trends using SQL, Power BI automated Dashboards.

Experience



Data Analyst

Makebot360 Technology Ltd.

Sep 2021 - Present (1 year 10 months)

- Utilizing analytics tools (Python, Power BI, and Excel) to obtain data, analyze data and generate meaningful insights.
- Produced monthly reports using advanced Excel spreadsheet functions.
- Created various Excel documents to assist with pulling metrics data and presenting information to stakeholders for concise explanations of best placement for needed resources.
- Upheld security and confidentiality of documents and data within area of responsibility.
- Collaborated with business-unit leaders to identify and prioritize problems.
- Utilized data visualization tools to effectively communicate business insights.
- Used statistical methods to analyze data and generate useful business reports.
- Identified, analyzed and interpreted trends or patterns in complex data sets.
- Developed required policies and procedures that reflected actual goals, tasks and workflows, while meeting all regulatory compliance requirements.
- Documented effective and replicable methods for extracting data and organizing data sources.

MAG

Business Analyst

Mad Science Group Inc.

Feb 2018 - Aug 2020 (2 years 7 months)

- Manipulating, cleansing & processing data using Excel, Access and SQL.
- Responsible for loading, extracting and validation of client data.
- · Analyzing raw data, drawing conclusions & developing recommendations
- Responsible for updating and maintaining Exchange fee pricing in the internal calculation system, which accurately captured MAD Science project execution fees rate.
- Worked on development and design of modules for migration of the team project.
- Analyzed open orders, backlog, and sales data to provide sales team with insights.
- Applied honed problem-solving skills to analyze and resolve issues impacting business operations and goal achievement.
- Analyzed key aspects of business to evaluate factors driving results and summarized into presentations.

- Developed and improved integrated reporting and analysis capabilities.
- Collaborated with stakeholders to define project objectives and criteria.
- Generated business intelligence reports to inform strategic decision-making.
- Performed gap analysis to identify areas of improvement.

Student Software Developer

Google Developer Group Ekiti State University

Feb 2014 - Jun 2017 (3 years 5 months)

- Contribute to collaborative in project designs and implementations.
- Design innovative approach to solving a new/existing problems.
- Headed a team of co-organizers to host meetups and hackathons' for tech enthusiasts and developers
- Acted as facilitator in training beginners on web development.
- Was responsible for setting up Internet presentations at industry trade shows.

Website Developer

OLYRUS CONSULTING GROUP

Oct 2011 - Feb 2013 (1 year 5 months)

- Planned website development, converting mockups into usable web presence with HTML, JavaScript, AJAX, and JSON coding.
- Provided front-end website development using WordPress, Hubspot, and other editing software. Coded websites using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and jQuery languages.
- Implemented Google-based SEO and ad campaigns to meet budget specifications.
- Collaborated with marketing, representing web team to establish project goals, projections and milestones.
- Multi-tasked across multiple functions and roles to meet deadlines and organizational expectations.
- Validated third-party code to comply with internal standards and technical requirements.
- Determined coding requirements for specialized scripts.
- Implemented content management and security resource tutorials to assist end-user training.
- Oversaw back-end development using PHP to maintain website integrity.

Education



University of Hull

Master's degree, Artificial Intelligence and Data Science Sep 2022 - Present

Program in-view



Ekiti State University, Ado-Ekiti

Bachelor's degree, Mathematics Aug 2013 - Sep 2017

Licenses & Certifications



Data Analysis with Python - freeCodeCamp

Skills

Python (Programming Language) • SQL • Data Analytics • Exploratory Data Analysis • Data Visualization • Microsoft Excel • MongoDB • Node.js • React.js • Data Science